<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Data Privacy Memo</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/</link><description>Recent content on Data Privacy Memo</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 10:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dataprivacymemo.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Privacy Tool Spotlight: EFF's Cover Your Tracks</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-09-privacy-tool-spotlight-cover/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-09-privacy-tool-spotlight-cover/</guid><description>&lt;p>Privacy isn&amp;rsquo;t just about complex regulations-—it&amp;rsquo;s about practical tools that give individuals real control. Recently I discovered &lt;a href="https://coveryourtracks.eff.org">Cover Your Tracks&lt;/a>, a free tool from the Electronic Frontier Foundation that does something surprisingly simple yet powerful: it shows you exactly how trackable you are online.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-cover-your-tracks">What Is Cover Your Tracks?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Developed by the Electronic Frontier Foundation, this web tool does a deep dive into your browser&amp;rsquo;s unique fingerprint. Most people have no idea how much information their own browser leaks about their identity, location, and browsing habits. Cover Your Tracks reveals the digital breadcrumbs you&amp;rsquo;re leaving behind without even realizing it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Five Surprising Ways Data Privacy Impacts Real Life</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-05-five-ways/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 14:39:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-05-five-ways/</guid><description>&lt;p>As I&amp;rsquo;ve been preparing to take the IAPP&amp;rsquo;s CIPP/E (European data privacy) certification, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to understand better just how data privacy shapes human experiences. As I dig deeper into my studies, five real-world scenarios straight from the headlines have helped me transform abstract legal concepts into urgent human stories.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-job-hunting-in-the-algorithmic-age">1. Job Hunting in the Algorithmic Age&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Automated processing&amp;rdquo; is a trending issue under the GDPR. Article 22 allows people to opt out of decisions based solely on algorithms, where the decision would affect their lives significantly. Automated screening systems are now everywhere in the workplace&amp;ndash;they parse resumes, social media profiles, and online footprints. A single tagged photo, an old tweet, or a data broker&amp;rsquo;s profile can silently eliminate job candidates. What seemed like a theoretical discussion about algorithmic decision-making is actually a critical employment equity issue.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>From Consumer Finance to Data Privacy</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-03-from-consumer-protection-to-data-privacy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 14:39:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-03-from-consumer-protection-to-data-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>When I started working as a fresh law school grad during the 2008 financial crisis in New York City, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know I was laying the groundwork for a journey into data privacy. My early work was about untangling complex financial concepts&amp;ndash;helping homeowners navigate predatory lending, understanding the intricate world of mortgage securitization, and breaking down seemingly impenetrable financial structures into something people could actually understand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For seventeen years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been a professional translator of complexity. Whether working through consumer bankruptcy issues or diving deep into the Fair Credit Reporting Act, my job was always about making the complicated comprehensible. I learned something crucial during those years: data isn&amp;rsquo;t just numbers or records. It&amp;rsquo;s the story of people&amp;rsquo;s lives, their financial struggles, their hopes, and their vulnerabilities.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>