<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Practical Privacy on Data Privacy Memo</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/categories/practical-privacy/</link><description>Recent content in Practical Privacy on Data Privacy Memo</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.146.7</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 10:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dataprivacymemo.com/categories/practical-privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Shaky Ground Underneath Cross-Border Data Transfers</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-21-cross-border/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-21-cross-border/</guid><description>&lt;p>In trying to understand the nuanced world of data privacy, I&amp;rsquo;ve been watching a critical transformation unfold in international data policy. The once-stable(ish) EU-US Data Privacy Framework is showing signs of strain as the U.S. executive branch flexes more power.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-perfect-storm-of-uncertainty">The Perfect Storm of Uncertainty&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A few recent developments are challenging the delicate balance of cross-border data transfers:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="executive-power-and-regulatory-flexibility">Executive Power and Regulatory Flexibility&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The US is signaling an expanded interpretation of executive authority over data policy. A recent declaration in the Federal Register by Secretary of State Marco Rubio suggests that &amp;ldquo;all efforts to control the transfer of data across US borders&amp;rdquo; could be considered a foreign affairs function. Translation? The executive branch might modify data transfer rules with minimal public input.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>GDPR's Right to Erasure: What to Know About the 2025 Coordinated Enforcement Action</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-12-edpb-coordinated-enforcement/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 09:05:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-12-edpb-coordinated-enforcement/</guid><description>The EDPB&amp;rsquo;s upcoming coordinated enforcement reveals critical challenges in implementing the right to be forgotten</description></item><item><title>Five Surprising Ways Data Privacy Impacts Real Life</title><link>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-05-five-ways/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 14:39:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://dataprivacymemo.com/posts/2025-03-05-five-ways/</guid><description>From algorithmic job screening to hidden healthcare data ecosystems, these real-world scenarios transform abstract concepts into urgent human stories.</description></item></channel></rss>